<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plaister for a galled horse Loke what here in shalbe redde wynse at nothyng, excepte ye be gylty for of vsurped power we be not a dradde, but God to be knowen, before preceptes fylthy we speake not agaynst Godes holy mystery but agaynst such, as loue neyther God nor theyr kynge beware therfore ye knowe not your desteny loke better to the Scripture, the word euerlastinge Yf this playster be to colde ye shall haue an other be bolde thintent is to cure and edyfy so it is sayd, by Ihon Ramsy</title>
            <author>Ramsay, John, 1496?-1551.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10386</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20662</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110585</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846099</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846099</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11044</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10386)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11044)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 140:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plaister for a galled horse Loke what here in shalbe redde wynse at nothyng, excepte ye be gylty for of vsurped power we be not a dradde, but God to be knowen, before preceptes fylthy we speake not agaynst Godes holy mystery but agaynst such, as loue neyther God nor theyr kynge beware therfore ye knowe not your desteny loke better to the Scripture, the word euerlastinge Yf this playster be to colde ye shall haue an other be bolde thintent is to cure and edyfy so it is sayd, by Ihon Ramsy</title>
                  <author>Ramsay, John, 1496?-1551.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Sainct Andrewes parysh in the wardrop by Thomas Raynalde],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.XLVIII. [1548]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An anti-Catholic verse satire.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and address from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: pi⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11044:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Plaiſter for a gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Horſe.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Loke what here in ſhalbe redde</l>
               <l>Wynſe at nothyng, excepte ye be grity</l>
               <l>For of vſurped power we be not a dradde.</l>
               <l>But God to be knowen, before preceptes fylthy</l>
               <l>We ſpeake not againſt Godes holy myſtery</l>
               <l>But agaynſt ſuch, as loue neyther God not theyr kynge</l>
               <l>Beware therfore ye knowe not your deſteny</l>
               <l>Loke better to the Scripture, the word euerlaſtinge</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prouerb. xxvi.</bibl>
               <p>Vnto the horſe be<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ongeth a whippe To the Aſſe a Brydleſ &amp; a rodde to the fooles backe.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <l>Yf this playſter be to colde</l>
               <l>Ye ſhall haue an other be bolde</l>
               <l>Thintent is to cure and edyfy</l>
               <l>So it is ſayd, By Jhon Ramſy</l>
            </q>
            <p>M. D. XLVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11044:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11044:2"/>
            <head>The plajſter.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He horſe that is gal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led wyll wynſe and kycke</l>
               <l>If any do enterpriſe, to come ſuch a nere</l>
               <l>He thinketh ye go about to touche the quicke</l>
               <l>That rather he wold runne thorow water and fire</l>
               <l>Euen the lyke our maſſemakers, begynne to ſtere</l>
               <l>If any in their maungines, fyndeth lacke</l>
               <l>Then lyke a galled horſe they ſtampe and ſtere</l>
               <l>But guppe ye godmakers beware your galled backe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Guppe ſyr Ihon and guppe Biſhoppe alſo</l>
               <l>Guppe al other, that holde with the ſame</l>
               <l>Very maungy ye are, and winſe to and fro</l>
               <l>Doubte not but at lengthe it wyll'turne you to ſhame</l>
               <l>For many of you commaunde in your owne name</l>
               <l>Vp with maſſe (we charge you let not that ſlacke</l>
               <l>Or els in the Caſtell of N. we wyll you tame</l>
               <l>But Guppe ye God makers, bewary your galled backe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What other are you, but maungy in dede</l>
               <l>To prefere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abhominacion moſt vyſe in Goddes ſighte</l>
               <l>Loke ye blynde dweles, in what Goſpell do ye rede</l>
               <l>That ſuche myrlymuſe, doth pleaſe God a ryght</l>
               <l>On thys ſyde, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſyde, as one ſought hys way by nighte</l>
               <l>Straining a knaues, armes, as though he ſtod on a rac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke</l>
               <l>With mockes and mowes, and like a foole dyght</l>
               <l>But guppe ye Godmakers, beware youre galled backe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thinke you Chriſten fayth to you is obedient</l>
               <l>To folow ſuch Mainetry, made by a pilled ſquier</l>
               <l>No no you maye well holde your ſelues content</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11044:3"/>
We haue neyther fayth, in Monke Prieſt nor Friet.</l>
               <l>ye are worthy to be hanged, and ſo payde for youre hiere</l>
               <l>That wyll compell, the trew ſubiectes to bear your packe</l>
               <l>It ſemeth by your dedes, that treaſon ye do conſpire</l>
               <l>But guppe ye Godmakers, be ware your galled backe:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wher is your obedience, and wher is your commiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</l>
               <l>So tyranly ſo heritikely, to geue any ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te</l>
               <l>To folow the pope, with hys ſuperſtytion</l>
               <l>yet in one knotte, to thys ye do conſente</l>
               <l>ye rore and crie, as men with oute Iudgement</l>
               <l>Vp wiſh the maſſe or eles al, goeth to wracke</l>
               <l>But remembre goodes vengaunce is ready bent</l>
               <l>And guppe ye Godmakers, beware your galled backe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ye ſay ye are an inſurrection</l>
               <l>But w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſhal it make. that wolde we knowe?</l>
               <l>Euen youre owne ſelues / with youre peſtilent Infection</l>
               <l>To ſupreſſe goddes veritie, and bringe it lowe,</l>
               <l>It is tyme to loke to you, for the ſede that you do ſowe</l>
               <l>Whych ye ſhall repe, and lay it on your owne ſtacke,</l>
               <l>We ſet not a fart by your maſſe made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mocke &amp; mowe</l>
               <l>But Guppe ye Godmakers, beware youre galled backe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Loke in holy ſcripture, learne there your dewtye</l>
               <l>ye bloode guides / that ſtomble at a ſtrawe</l>
               <l>There ſhall ye fynde, that the Lorde God onely,</l>
               <l>Shalte thou ſerue and folowe his holy law</l>
               <l>But thou thinkeſte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god is made of euery Iackedawe</l>
               <l>As in his handes thou muſt heare his bones cracke</l>
               <l>And thynkeſt thy ſelfe ſafe. when he is downe in thy maw</l>
               <l>But Guppe ye Godmakers, beware your galled backe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>you<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> maſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye make your god ſerueth for many a thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge</l>
               <l>For <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>e for drowthe, for peſtilence and ſhepe</l>
               <l>For <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>gges for pylgrimes, for ſhippes that he ſaylynge</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11044:3"/>
For corne for the cough, and for thoſe that can not ſlepe</l>
               <l>And what for thys yf your god ye do not well kepe</l>
               <l>He will ſtynke in his houſe, ye can not a byde the ſmacke</l>
               <l>yet to that falſe god, ye knele and crepe</l>
               <l>But guppe ye godmakers beware your galled backe:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>you haue chaplens of truſt, that ſerue for the nones</l>
               <l>Gredy of ſtommacke haſty in digeſtion</l>
               <l>That can eate vp a whole body both fleſh bloud &amp; bones</l>
               <l>And that ſame daye be dronke and aſke no queſtion</l>
               <l>A dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chaplen a dronken god, ſurely a holy profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>Curſed be ſuch for ther dedes are blacke</l>
               <l>Our God is in heauen, whych dyed for our redemption</l>
               <l>But puppe ye godmakers beware your galled backe:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In thre partes your God muſt be deuyded</l>
               <l>For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodyes aboue, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodyes beneth, &amp; thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be lyui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge</l>
               <l>That Pope was wyſe that thus had contryued</l>
               <l>God for God, God for the dyuell, God for all yll doynge</l>
               <l>Euery pice was God, thys is your teichinge</l>
               <l>So that the leaſt piece, be it neuer ſo lytle a ſnacke</l>
               <l>Is god of god made, that had a begynnyng</l>
               <l>But guppe ye godmakers. beware your galled backe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>ye may do what ye lyſte with thinges of youre owne</l>
               <l>ye may do what ye can, where ye be not ſet by.</l>
               <l>your cruell tormentes be ſone ouer blowen,</l>
               <l>And the rekeninge ye muſte make of all your Iniurie</l>
               <l>Men that accompte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues wyſe ſhuld circumſpectly</l>
               <l>Do all thinges to gods honor, &amp; not his ſcripture hacke</l>
               <l>As men de lekes, their Imagination to ſatyſfy</l>
               <l>But guppe ye godmakers beware your galled backe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We wolde talke with you, but your malice is to greate</l>
               <l>your dedes do declare, ye are the Popes Pygges</l>
               <l>yet we wil ax one queſtion but be in no more heate</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11044:4"/>
And let by heare what ye ſucked out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Popes biggis</l>
               <l>Do men on the brembles gather any figges</l>
               <l>do your horemaſters preſtes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by their miniſtracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>packe</l>
               <l>To alure Chriſt out of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do byrdes to twing<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges</l>
               <l>No no, ye Godmakes / beware your galled backe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Chriſt ſitteth in heauen holy ſcripture ſaith ſo,</l>
               <l>Chriſt ſhall come agayne, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame body y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wente hence</l>
               <l>Chriſt ſaid it was expedient that he ſhuld go</l>
               <l>For his fleſhly body dyd no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger profyt by preſence</l>
               <l>The kyſſe that Iudas had toke not a waye hys offence</l>
               <l>But ſtill in deſperation. his conſecience ſtacke</l>
               <l>Moche leſſe in your God, that hath no intelligence</l>
               <l>But guppe ye Godmakers, beware your galled backe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ye pretende a great holynes, but not in right vſe</l>
               <l>Chriſtes inſtitution is cleane out of memory</l>
               <l>He brake the bread, without bayne excuſe</l>
               <l>And ſayde it was hys body that endes ſhulde dye</l>
               <l>Now it was not the bread: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was crucifyed at Caluarye</l>
               <l>But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body whych is i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thys ſcripture ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not lac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke</l>
               <l>And as the bread was broken euen ſo was his body</l>
               <l>But Gup ye God makers, beware your galled backe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But as you do vſe it, it is neither here nor there</l>
               <l>But a faynde mommer<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, of Antichriſtes deuyſe</l>
               <l>And as Baruch ſayth no God he is, we nede not to feare</l>
               <l>For when he is downe he can no more ryſe</l>
               <l>Yet your Priſtes, handell him ſo fynely and nyce</l>
               <l>Wrappe him in clowtes, with many apopyſhe knacke</l>
               <l>I wolde all ſuch priſtes, mighty ſwarme ful of lyce</l>
               <l>But guppe ye Godmakers, beware your galled backe:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lay forth for your ſelfe, the beſt that ye can</l>
               <l>Commounde what ye lyſt, of your owne deuyſe</l>
               <l>We knowe, ye ſhal not be obayed of neuer an honeſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11044:4"/>
But of your owne couenauntes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> popes guyſe</l>
               <l>yet beware leaſt your heades knowe the pryce</l>
               <l>for ye lyke trayters, againſt our kyng fynde lacke</l>
               <l>in ſuppreſſing the Pope, with all his marchaundyce</l>
               <l>But guppe ye godmakers beware your galle backe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Marke the geſture, who that lyſt</l>
               <l>Firſt a ſhorne ſhauelynge, clad in a clowt</l>
               <l>Bearinge the name of an honeſt prieſt</l>
               <l>And yet in no place a ſtarker lowte</l>
               <l>A whore monger a dronkard, ye mayken hym be ſnowte</l>
               <l>At the Alehouſes he ſtudieth, tyll hys wirte he doth lacke</l>
               <l>Such are your min<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſters, to bringe thys matter about</l>
               <l>But guppe ye godmakers. be ware youe galled backe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then wraped in a knaues ſkynne, as holy as my horſe</l>
               <l>Before the aulter, in great contemplacion</l>
               <l>Confeſſinge the ſynnes of his lubbryſh Corſe</l>
               <l>To god and all ſaynctes, he counteth hys abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>Then home to the aulter, with great ſaintification</l>
               <l>With croſſes, and bleſſes, with his boy lytle Iacke</l>
               <l>Thus forth goeth ſyr Ihon with all his preparation</l>
               <l>But puppe ye godmakers beware your galled backe:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then gloria in excelſis for ioye dothe he ſynge</l>
               <l>More for his fat lyuinge, then for deuocion</l>
               <l>And many there be that remember another thinge</l>
               <l>Which ſyng not wyth mery hart for l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cke of promocion</l>
               <l>Thus ſome be mery, ſome be ſory according to their por<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>The forth comet <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Colettes, bounde vp in a packe</l>
               <l>Of this ſainct and that ſainct, for ſickenes, and extorcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>But guuppeye godmakers beware your galled backe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The epiſtell and goſpell they haue put in</l>
               <l>To colour their falſe'hed vnder holy pretence</l>
               <l>And al in latyn, to cloke their ſynnne,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11044:5"/>
This daylie is ſene by common experience</l>
               <l>Now marke, for here cometh great reuerence,</l>
               <l>Adappe for a flye, whiche is a prety knacke</l>
               <l>T<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at muſt ye kyſſe, and gyue them pence</l>
               <l>But guppe ye godmakers beware your galled backe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt be waſh, he hath handled ſome whores tayle</l>
               <l>With tourne about Iacke / and ſhew ſome ſporte</l>
               <l>For many at popiſh knaues, of the ſhauen ſorte</l>
               <l>More me<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er he were for the whippe and flayle,</l>
               <l>Then to put the dead ſoules in good comfort</l>
               <l>Ther ſtandeth <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e moming lyke a calfe in a ſacke</l>
               <l>Many tymes hy<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whore, wyll the ther reſorte</l>
               <l>But guppe ye godmakers beware your galled backe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then make they god wyth wordes ynowe</l>
               <l>And hange hym vp betwene theues twayne</l>
               <l>Then ye maſmongers, loke that ye bowe</l>
               <l>For there is your god, made by a knaue in graine</l>
               <l>And he prayeth vnto him for all ſyckenes and payne</l>
               <l>And at length doth eate hym, bothe ſhoulder leg &amp; tacke</l>
               <l>And the next daye can make an other agayne</l>
               <l>But guppe ye godmakers, beware your galled backe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus ye are begyled with ſuche foxes play</l>
               <l>And your hartes are ſo fet that the truth ye do not ſee</l>
               <l>yet remember god and our kynge what they do ſay</l>
               <l>That from Idolatry wolde haue you to flee,</l>
               <l>yf ye wyll not then be blynde ſtyll for me:</l>
               <l>the lord defend our noble king, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of you he haue no lacke</l>
               <l>For you ar hard to be truſted what ſoeuer ye be</l>
               <l>Therfore year warned, beware your galled backe</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London in Sainet Indrewes Paryſh in the wardrop By Thomas Raynalde</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
